<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="storyContents">
        <item>When Sudama went to Dwaraka, his childhood friend Sri Krishna and his wife Rukmini, received him with affection. They persuaded Sudama to stay with them for a few days. Then they took him back to his village in their chariot.Meanwhile, in the village, word spread that Sri Krishna was coming to their village. Villagers began to gather in Sudama’s cottage.“Sri Krishna and Rukmini are visiting our Sudama’s house. We must make it fit for their visit,” said an elder.“Let’s build a new home for our Sudama,” cried out a villager and all agreed.The villagers worked day and night to build a big and spacious house, and decorated it with festoons. They brought new clothes and ornaments for Sudama’s family. They drew Rangoli (Kolam) in front of Sudama’s house and decorated it with flowers.Sudama’s wife thanked the villagers for their affection.Villagers lined up on both sides of the streets hailing Sri Krishna as he drove by. Sri Krishna stopped the chariot, jumped down and mingled with the villagers. Girls came running to him with dandiya and Sri Krishna danced with them.At last, the procession reached Sudama’s house. Sudama’s wife brought water for Sri Krishna and Rukmini to wash their feet. Sudama wiped their feet dry with the cloth his wife gave him. His children fell at Sri Krishna’s feet.“Bhabhi,” said Sri Krishna, “I’m hungry. What do you have for me?”Sudama’s wife smiled.“Govinda, I offer you what you have given us,” she said.
            Then she brought him a bowl full of butter!Sri Krishna jumped with joy as Rukmini clapped. The villagers joined their hands in salutation as Sri Krishna put the butter into his mouth.</item>
        <item>He was a visitor to Dwaraka. Draped in an ordinary looking cloth round his waist, a piece of cloth across his shoulders, and a bag hanging from his left shoulder, the stranger walked barefoot. His hair was combed and tied. He walked leisurely, neither too fast nor too slow, looking straight ahead, unmindful of stares that followed him.

The stranger headed straight to the palace. The guard outside the palace became alert. Tall, well built and with a thick moustache stretching from ear to ear and a huge helmet with two horns, he was a fearsome figure. Behind his back, people of Dwaraka called him Rakshasa, a demon, with enormous power, captured in a battle by Krishna, the Yadava hero. No doubt, he was devoted to his new Master, but the citizens of Dwaraka kept their distance.

Rakshasa frowned seeing the stranger approaching the palace. He was used to princes and kings arriving to meet his Master. He was glad to escort dignitaries to the courtyard of the palace. Never had he seen such a poor man approaching the palace. Intending to stop the unwelcome guest, he stepped forward.

Just then, Sri Krishna came out of the palace. Seeing the stranger, he broke into a broad smile and ran to him, calling out, “Sudama, my friend, what a surprise!” Rakshasa froze as he saw Sri Krishna hugging the visitor! The visitor with tears of joy, hugged Sri Krishna calling him ‘Govinda.’

Hearing that a guest had arrived, Sri Krishna’s wife Rukmini came to the door. She brought water for the guest to wash his feet. Sri Krishna wiped his feet with the silken cloth he was wearing and made him sit on the swing. The two friends started talking about old times, as Rukmini sat close by fanning them gently.

Sri Krishna and Sudama were classmates in Guru Sandipani’s forest school. Patting his friend on the back, Sri Krishna said, “So you are married! Bhabhi must have sent something for me. Let me see what’s in your bag.” Sri Krishna took Sudama’s bag and dug into it. He took out a small packet wrapped in cloth. Sudama smiled as Sri Krishna eagerly opened the bundle, watched by Rukmini.

Sudama smiled thinking of his wife he loved. Of late, he was thinking of his childhood mate, Govinda. He mentioned this to his wife. She urged him to go to Dwaraka and meet his friend. “You have been taking about your friend so long. You’d better go and meet him. He too will be happy to see you,” said his wife.

As he was about to leave, she gave him a packet bundled in a piece of cloth and said, “When you call on those you love and respect, you must give them something. Here is something I’ve put for your dear friend,” she said. Sudama thanked her and put it into his bag as he left for Dwaraka. He had no idea what his wife had given for Sri Krishna.

Now he would know, as Sri Krishna opened the bundle. It was poha, made from pounded rice!

Even the poorest of the poor manage to get some poha to fill their stomach. It is a poor man’s friend. What Sri Krishna saw in that poha was tremendous love his friend and his wife had for him. That made it divine. He eagerly stuffed his mouth with handful of poha as though he had not eaten for months! Sudama laughed with delight as Rukmini watched with a smile. Sri Krishna dipped into the packet and put into his mouth one more handful of poha with relish. As he munched poha rolling his eyes, Rukmini snatched the bag from Sri Krishna. “Spare something for me,” she said as Sudama burst out laughing.

Rukmini served a lavish lunch. Krishna himself served sweets to his friend. After lunch, Sudama wanted to leave. Both Sri Krishna and Rukmini urged him to spend a couple of days with him. “I want you to take us to your home. We want to meet Bhabhi,” said Krishna as Rukmini nodded her head in agreement.


</item>
        <item>
            Kamsa sent Pootana to Gokula to kill the child born to Chief Nanda. Later, he received news that Pootana had died mysteriously.
Kamsa was disappointed that his trusted lieutenant Pootana was dead while the child in Gokula was unharmed. His minister pointed out that they knew now where the enemy was: in Gokula. Kamsa’s spirits lifted. He summoned a demon, known for his ability to remain invisible and assume various forms. His mission was simple: Kill Krishna!

Meanwhile, baby Krishna had started rolling over. He could now lie on his tummy and lift his head. He would soon crawl on all fours. This called for celebrations. Gopis poured into Yashoda’s house, singing songs with lighted lamps in their hands. As the whole village celebrated, the demon entered Gokula.

The demon decided to wait for an opportune time to strike. He spotted a decorated hand cart parked in Nanda’s courtyard. He hid in the cart, invisible to all.The ladies were busy with the ceremony. Baby Krishna was put in a cradle as the ladies sang lullabies. Little Krishna moved his hands and legs in delight. Soon, he fell asleep. Yashoda looked for a place where her child would not be disturbed as he slept peacefully. The house was full of giggling girls and gossiping women. Yashoda spotted a quiet place — the courtyard. She placed the cradle with the sleeping Krishna below the decorated hand cart parked in the courtyard. Little did she know that a demon was lying low, right there in the cart!

The demon hiding in the cart could not believe his luck. His prey was brought to his very den! He smirked with satisfaction as he prepared to strike.

Meanwhile the child woke up. He playfully kicked his leg. The soft leg touched the cart which flew in the air and came crashing down on the ground. As the cart crashed down, the earth shook, and the vessels in the cart rolled out with a loud, clattering noise. Hearing the noise, the women came out to see what had happened.

Yashoda screamed when she saw the fallen cart and ran towards it to pull her child to safety. Little Krishna crawled out smiling. Yashoda lifted the child and hugged him. Only then did she notice a demon lying dead. The ladies screamed. Nanda came running.

Nanda and other elders were bewildered to see the demon lying dead! Where did that cart giant, Shakatasura, come from and why? There was no answer to the mystery.
        </item>
        <item>
            The cart giant, Shakatasura had failed in his mission to kill Krishna. Kamsa to ponder over his next move.
Kamsa was stunned to hear that Shakatasura, the cart demon, was dead. He refused to believe that the helpless infant was the cause of his death. Even so, he was cautious when sending the next assassin on a mission to kill the child growing in Gokula.

“Powerful demons like Pootana and Shakatasura have met their end,” said Kamsa, warning the demon Trinavrata, who had volunteered to go to Gokula.

“Had you sent me in the first place, my friends Pootana and Shakatasura would be alive today,” said Trinavrata.

Kamsa was impressed with his confidence. Trinavrata left for Gokula the same day.

It was evening in Gokula when Trinavrata arrived. Yashoda was admiring her little son lying in her lap with a smile. Suddenly she felt weak. She felt her child was too heavy. She lowered Krishna to the floor so that she could relax. Just then she noticed the sky darkening. Trees shook. The temperature dropped. The next moment there was a rush of wind raising dust, which flooded the house. Protectively, Yashoda tried to reach for Krishna. But she could not see anything in the air thick with dust. She started moving her hands in all directions to gather the child on the floor. She seemed to be gathering only dust. To reassure the child, she started calling his name, “Krishna, Krishna.”Gradually, the wind weakened. The dust settled down. The sky brightened. Yashoda could see now. She found her little Krishna gone. “Krishna!” she screamed as she ran out of the house looking for the child.

The demon Trinavrata had assumed the form of a whirlwind. He had carried little Krishna high in the air. The demon was pleasantly surprised that he could carry away his victim so easily. The first part of his mission achieved. What remained was an easy task — to hurl the child against a huge rock and end his life.

Just as he spotted a huge rock, the demon was surprised to find the child getting heavier. Krishna was as light as a feather when Trinavrata had lifted him, now he had become as heavy as a grinding stone! The demon decided to drop him. To his horror, he found he could not drop the baby as the little one had clasped his hands round his neck. He gasped for breath as Krishna tightened his grip. Trinavrata dropped down dead.

The cowherds of Gokula came running when they heard a loud sound. They saw the demon sprawled out on the ground, dead. Little Krishna as usual was crawling playfully near him. Yashoda ran to pick up her child. Even as she hugged the child, Nanda looked up the sky, saying a silent prayer to God above.
        </item>
        <item>
            People of Mathura braced up to face a new menace — a baby killer out on prowl looking for new born infants. The baby killer was Kamsa’s agent out to kill the newly born baby who was going to be the destroyer of all evil.

Nanda, the Chief of Gokula, came to Mathura with tribute for the king. Paying the tribute to Kamsa, he told him about the birth of a son. Kamsa complemented him, and as soon as Nanda left, Kamsa summoned Pootana, and asked her to leave for Gokula immediately. “A child was born in Nanda’s household on the very day Yogamaya told me that my enemy is born elsewhere. I suspect this child to be the one she was speaking about,” said Kamsa, “Use your charms, get that child on your lap and feed him your poison,” ordered Kamsa.

Chief Nanda decided to spend a day in Mathura. He called on his friend Vasudeva and gave him and Devaki sweets he had brought from Gokula. “Your son Balarama has company. Yashoda delivered a boy. We have called him Krishna,” said Vasudeva. Devaki’s heart skipped a beat. She softly said to herself, “Krishna, Krishna, Krishna…” Vasudeva patted her to calm her and then turned to Nanda.

“My friend I’m glad you are a proud father of a boy. For some time, I feel, you must take care of your people. I’ve a feeling something horrible may happen if you are careless. I pray to Lord Hari (Vishnu) for your safety,” said Vasudeva.

Meanwhile, Pootana had reached Gokula. She easily found her way to Chief Nanda’s house where the celebration was still going on. Women were moving in and out of the house carrying sweets, girls were dancing and elders were busy offering worship. Many women were at the house to greet Yashoda. Pootana, clad in a silk sari, covered with ornaments and jasmine flowers hanging from plaited hair looked like one of them. She walked in and headed straight to the hall where ladies were admiring the newly born son of Nanda. Pootana patted the child lovingly and gathered him in her arms.

Somebody called Yashoda and she went out, leaving the child alone with the visitor. Pootana entered a room, put the child on her lap in order to feed it. The innocent child smiled at her as it trustingly reached her breast. Pootana had a twinge of guilt. “What am I doing?” she wondered, “Is this the life I want to live?” Overcome by guilt, even as she fed the little one the poisonous milk, Pootana desperately thought, “I’d rather die than live this kind of wretched life.” Just then she noticed the little baby smiling at her and she was filled with the kind of peace she never knew before.

Meanwhile an elderly lady stopped Yashoda and asked her, “Where is Krishna?” Yashoda told her she had left the child with a kind lady. “Do you know who she is?” asked the elderly woman. “Don’t you know a baby killer is roaming around?” she shouted at Yashoda.

Yashoda ran inside. The hall was deserted. The child and the woman were nowhere to be seen. Fearing the worst, Yashoda started searching for them in various rooms. Then she heard her little son making slurping noise. She rushed into the room and stood stunned.

Her son, Krishna, was safe and was smiling. Next to him was a woman lying on the floor in her demon form!

Yashoda ran and gathered her darling son in her arms. Other women came in and were frightened to see the demon lying dead. Meanwhile, Nanda who was approaching Gokula, heard the commotion and ran to his house. Yashoda ran to him with Krishna in her arms.

Nanda and other cowherds dragged the body of the dead demon out and performed funeral rites. Strangely, the air was filled with fragrance, which was hardly noticed by Nanda. He was lost in thought. “Is this calamity Vasudeva was hinting at?” Nanda wondered.
        </item>
        <item>
            A voice heard from the sky had announced that the eighth son of Vasudeva and Devaki was going to be the destroyer of evil. Afraid for his life, Kamsa, Devaki’s cousin, had vowed to kill every child born to Devaki. However, using her magic, Devi Yogamaya arranged for the eighth child to be transferred to the village of Gokula in the middle of the night. The child was now in the house of Nanda and Yashoda, who took the baby for their own child and named him Krishna.

Kamsa set Vasudeva and Devaki free. “Believing that the child born to you will grow into my enemy, I killed all those innocent infants. That voice from the sky lied. Now I understand my enemy is born somewhere else. Pardon me, if you can,” said Kamsa.

Kamsa met his advisers. “The gods have deceived me. My destroyer is safe somewhere,” he said looking nervous.

“Nothing is impossible for the Lord of Mathura,” said an advisor. “You can still kill your enemy. After all he is a helpless suckling baby.”

“But how? I do not know who he is or where he is,” said Kamsa.

“Let’s kill all the babies born this week in our kingdom,” suggested an old and wicked minister.

Even as Kamsa’s face brightened at this suggestion, a young minister cautioned him, “If we kill babies, we’ll get a bad name. People will despise us as baby killers. They may even rise in rebellion.”

“I can trust Pootana to do it without drawing attention,” said Kamsa.

Kamsa had in his service a hoard of rakshasas with magical powers. One of them, Pootana, could fly, change her form and draw blood. But even Pootana found the job entrusted to her revolting.

“Lord, you want me to kill babies! I’ve never stooped so low before,” Pootana protested.

“Pootana, an enemy has to be nipped in the bud. If we allow him to grow up, he will kill not only me, also my entire army — including you,” said Kamsa. “Besides, you have no choice. You have to obey my command!”

Thus silenced, Pootana set out on her mission — to kill suckling infants.

Pootana stood in front of the mirror. Looking at herself, she smiled. “No baby would ever come to me with such a terrible look,” she thought. The next moment, she changed herself into a loving woman with a motherly look and set out from her home, looking for her victims.

She heard a faint cry from a house. She walked into the house and spoke gently to the mother. “Your baby seems to be hungry.”

“I know,” said the mother looking sad. “He’s always hungry. I don’t have enough milk for him.”

“Let me feed your child,” said Pootana, as she picked up the baby.

Entrusting the baby to the woman who looked so kind, the mother turned to household chores. Soon the baby stopped crying and the mother busy in the kitchen was happy that a kindly woman had satisfied her child. After finishing her work, she came out to thank the kind-hearted lady. But she found her gone and the baby sleeping peacefully. As she picked up the baby she noticed it had turned blue. Concerned, she called the physician who looked at the baby and nodded his head sadly. The woman was heart-broken to hear that her baby had died of poisoning.

Soon news came from all parts of Mathura — a baby killer was out on the street and she killed babies by breast feeding them with poisonous milk. Mothers were advised not to trust strangers. Yet, when Pootana with her motherly look appeared nobody suspected her. They simply trusted her, only to regret later.
        </item>
        <item>
            This happened in the Krita Yuga (Golden Age). Hiranyaksha, an asura, dived into the ocean. To rescue earth, Lord Vishnu assumed the form of a wild boar, Varaaha, and went after the asura. Varaaha overpowered Hiranyaksha in the duel that he fought under the water, and restored earth to its original position in the universe.

Varaaha achieved this magnificent feat with apparent ease, and the only sign of his exertion was a drop of sweat, which fell on the ground. A fully grown young warrior arose from this drop of Lord Varaaha’s sweat. His name was Naraka.

Bhoodevi or Mother Earth took a liking to this son of hers and asked Lord Varaaha that her son should become invincible. Varaaha pulled out one of his tusks and gave it to Naraka saying he could use it as a weapon whenever he was in great danger.

“Use your great powers to do only good, son,” said Lord Varaaha. “Uphold dharma.”

Naraka went away to seek his fortune.

“I’ve no doubt he will become the most powerful warrior in the three worlds,” said Bhoodevi expressing admiration for her son.

“Powerful, he will certainly be,” said Lord Varaaha. “Will he also uphold dharma? What makes an individual great is his adherence to dharma.”

Centuries rolled by. Krita Yuga was followed by Treta Yuga and then came Dwapara Yuga (we are in the Kali Yuga that followed the Dwapara Yuga). By then, people who had acquired power but brushed aside dharma had grown in number. Simply put, upholding dharma means being kind, truthful, caring and helpful. Its opposite, adharma, means being untruthful, arrogant, violent and destructive.

Lord Vishnu would take birth on earth to uphold dharma and to root out adharma. Each of his births is called an avatar or the descent of the Lord.

In the Dwapara Yuga, Lord Vishnu had come down to Earth as Krishna, the Yadava hero. He vanquished his wicked uncle Kamsa. He brought about the destruction of kings who were not adhering to dharma.

Meanwhile, Naraka had grown very powerful. Ruling from his impregnable fortress of Prag-jyotisha-pura or the land of the rising sun, he had conquered earth and heaven. Drunk with power, he snatched away the celestial ear rings of Aditi, the mother of the devas.

Indra, the Lord of the devas, sought Krishna’s help to vanquish the invincible Naraka. Sathyabhama, one of Krishna’s wives, was upset when she heard about the misdeeds of Naraka. She urged her husband to act. Armed with his Sudarshana chakra and other weapons, Krishna left for Prag-joyitisha-pura. Sathyabhama went with him. Both of them rode on Garuda, the celestial eagle, which served as a vehicle for Krishna.

To strike at Naraka’s capital, Krishna had to penetrate four layers of its defenses. He flew over the outermost ring of walls made of rocks, he crossed the rings of fire and of spears. Whoever tried to stop him was struck down. The chief defender of Naraka’s fort was Mura. Confident that none could penetrate the rings of defenses he had set up, Mura was relaxing deep down in the ring of water. As each layer of defense crumbled under Krishna’s attack, it caused violent ripples in the water, arousing Mura out of his slumber. Then he heard an ear shattering sound — it was Krishna blowing his conch, Panchajanya.

Enraged, Mura rushed out to stage a counter attack. He fell fighting Krishna, who earned the name, Muraari, the enemy of Mura.

Ultimately Naraka himself came out of his palace to battle Krishna. The two fought day and night. It was hard to say who was more powerful. Naraka was saving the weapon given to him by his father, Lord Varaaha, precisely for such an occasion. On the dark night of Chaturdashi, the fourteenth day of the fortnight of new moon, Naraka took out the deadly tusk of Lord Varaaha and threw it at Krishna. Struck in the chest Krishna fell unconscious. Even as Naraka raised a cry of victory, Sathyabhama picked up the bow and continued the fight. In Satyabhama, Naraka found a worthy foe. He had no clue as to how to stop her onslaught.

As the duel between the two raged on, Krishna opened his eyes. Naraka was startled to see Krishna stand up. If the dreaded weapon of Lord Varaaha had failed, it meant only one thing — his opponent was none other than Lord Varaaha himself, his father. Naraka was dazed. Lord Varaaha’s warning words now rang in his ears: “Use your powers to do only good, son. Uphold dharma.”

He had failed to follow his father’s advice. He meekly submitted, as Krishna threw his Sudarshana chakra at him.

As his life was webbing away, Naraka joined his hands in salutation to Krishna and Sathyabhama. Moved at the sight of the fallen asura, Sathyabhama rushed to him.

Krishna silently watched the reunion of mother and son. Sathyabhama was none other than Bhoodevi, born again!

Naraka saw the light in his dying moments. The darkness was lifted as the dawn broke. That day is celebrated as the festival of lights, Deepavali or Diwali, which signifies that we have to emerge from darkness to light.

(Adapted from the Mahabharata and the Bhagavata Purana.)
        </item>
        <item>
            Mathura slept blissfully under the spell of Devi Yogamaya on the night that Krishna was born. But Vasudeva, Krishna’s father, did not feel blissful. He was fully focussed on getting his eighth son to safety. He had carried his son to the village of Gokula in a basket, and left him at his friend Nanda’s house. He had placed his son next to Nanda’s wife Yashoda, and had left with her new born baby girl.

Back in Mathura, Vasudeva entered the prison. He lowered the basket and gently placed the female child next to his wife Devaki. The child cried and the spell was broken. The guards woke up and informed Kamsa.

As Kamsa approached the child, Vasudeva tried to stop him. “Kamsa, do not touch the child. It is a girl.”

“Girl or boy, the eighth child of Devaki is my enemy,” said Kamsa.

Devaki held the child close to her. Kamsa snatched the child from her. The next moment, to his shock, the child flew out of his hands and escaped from the window. As Kamsa ran out, chasing the child, which had reached the sky, the voice of Devi Yogamaya was heard loudly. “You fool, the destroyer of evil, the eighth child of Devaki is born elsewhere.” With that the voice fell silent.

Kamsa suddenly felt weak in his legs. “Are the Devas plotting against me?” he wondered. He was afraid for his life. “The destroyer of evil is born elsewhere,” he muttered as he collapsed.

Gradually, Kamsa recovered. He stood up and clenched his fists. Looking up at the sky, and shaking his fists in rage, he thundered, “I’ll find Devaki’s eighth son wherever he is, and I’ll destroy him.”

When Devaki heard him, she broke down. “Was all this for nothing? Will my child never be safe?” Vasudeva consoled her, “Do not be afraid, Devaki. Kamsa cannot harm your son for He is the Protector of the Universe, Lord Vishnu himself.”

Devaki and Vasudeva joined their hands, closed their eyes and prayed.
        </item>
        <item>
            The eighth son of Vasudeva and Devaki was destined to be the destroyer of evil. Afraid for his life, Kamsa, Devaki’s cousin, had vowed to kill every child born to Devaki. However, using her magic, Devi Yogamaya arranged for the child to be transferred to the village of Gokula in the middle of the night. The child was now in the house of Nanda and Yashoda, who took the baby for their own child.

In Gokula, next to Chief Nanda’s house lived Rohini, Vasudeva’s first wife, with her son Balarama. In fact, Balarama was the seventh child of Devaki. To protect the child from Kamsa, Yogamaya had moved the child even before he was born to Rohini’s womb. Thus, Balarama was born in Gokula.

It was Rohini who first heard the cry of the baby apparently born in the house of Chief Nanda. She rushed out of her house, with Balarama closely behind. She entered Nanda’s house and was delighted to see the baby boy born to her friend, Yashoda. She hugged her friend and kissed the new born. “You have a little brother now, Balarama,” she said to her son. Balarama smiled at Yashoda’s child.

Nanda heard ladies talking and came there. He was delighted that his wife had given birth to a boy.

Nobody knew that they were looking at Devaki’s eighth child.

It was time to celebrate. People of the village gathered at Chief Nanda’s house. Sweets were distributed. Ladies sang songs. Girls danced.

Their Chief Nanda now was a proud father.

Nanda named his son Krishna.

People of Gokula called the child Nandalala. Some called him Nanda Gopala. He was dark in complexion and handsome. So, he was called Shyama Sundara.

Everyone in the village was happy. But little did they know that danger lurked and dark forces summoned by Kamsa were out to get Nandalala.
        </item>
        <item>It was midnight when Krishna was born. Outside, it was raining heavily. The Yamuna river close by, was flooded. Clouds covered the moon, so there was little light. Inside the prison cell, it was warm, as Devaki hugged her new born son, who was smiling at her. But Devaki and her husband Vasudeva were too frightened to smile. They looked nervously at the locked gate of the prison. No guards showed their faces. This meant they did not know yet that the eighth child was born. That meant Kamsa, the King of Mathura, too did not know about the birth.

Just a few years ago, Kamsa had been a devoted brother to Devaki. They were cousins and very close to each other. On the day of her marriage, the newly married couple were taken in a procession, and Kamsa himself drove the chariot.

Amid the jubilation, rising over the beating of drums, a voice was heard, loud and clear. “The eighth child of Devaki will be the destroyer of all evil in this world.” Everyone was happy to hear the divine voice. Devaki’s son would bring in the good times.

Only one person was shaken to hear the divine oracle — Kamsa. His father, Ugrasena, used to warn him time and again, “you have strength and power. I only wish you pay attention to Dharma. You must use your strength and power for the good of everyone.” Kamsa would disagree. “Only the fittest will survive,” he would argue, “I adore strength and power. I want to inspire fear in people so that no one will pose a threat to me.”

Now he could see a threat to him. Kamsa winced. “I must nip it in the bud.”

Thus, as the voice from the heavens heralded the coming of the Destroyer of Evil, at that very moment, evil raised its head in Kamsa.

One moment Kamsa was full of love for his cousin. The next moment, his love turned into hatred. He pulled the reign and brought the chariot to a halt. He drew out of his sword and charged at the bride. He would have killed her had Vasudeva not come in between.“Devaki has done you no harm, Kamsa,” said Vasudeva in a quiet voice.

“Do you expect me to do nothing when the child that she will deliver is going to kill me?” asked Kamsa.

“The voice said no such thing. But I can understand if you have reasons to hate the child that will be born to her one day. But you have no reason to hate Devaki,” pointed out Vasudeva. “Spare her life. We will hand over to you every child that will be born to us.”

Kamsa reluctantly agreed. But to ensure that the couple would not run away, he threw them in prison. When Ugrasena tried to stop him, he threw the old king too into prison, and occupied the throne.

Vasudeva was already married to Rohini. When her husband was taken a prisoner, Rohini moved to Gokula, a village on the other bank of the Yamuna. She took a house next to the house of Nanda, the Village Chief and a friend of Vasudeva.

In Mathura, Kamsa put Devaki’s little sons to death as soon as they were born. But when Devaki’s seventh child was about to be born, Devi Yogamaya decided to save the child. The child about to be born was miraculously transferred to Rohini, who delivered the baby the very next day in Gokula.

Unaware of the trick played on him, Kamsa thought that Devaki’s seventh child was dead. He wished the eighth child too would meet such an end. But he was not prepared to take chances. He posted more guards to keep a watch on Devaki. The guards were told that he should be informed as soon as the eighth child was born. He would come to the prison, pick up the baby and would kill it with his own hands.

Now that the eighth son was born, Devaki shivered with fear. Vasudeva anxiously looked at the prison gate, fearing that Kamsa would walk in at any moment.</item>
        <item>
            Devaki and Vasudeva’s eighth child, Krishna, was destined to be the destroyer of evil. This made Devaki’s brother, Kamsa, very nervous. He had thrown Devaki and Vasudeva in prison and killed the six children born to them. Devi Yogamaya had protected the seventh child using her magic. A few months later, on a rainy night, Krishna was born.

Kamsa had Vasudeva tied up in chains. Any attempt to escape was impossible. But as soon as Krishna was born, to Vasudeva’s surprise, the chains fell off! He kissed his new born son and hugged his wife.

“This is no ordinary child. He will be our deliverer. It is our duty to protect this eighth child of yours, the saviour of the Universe,” said Vasudeva.

“But how can we protect him? Kamsa will be here any moment,” said Devaki.

Vasudeva folded up their blankets to made a soft bedding and placed it in the basket. He tenderly picked up the new born child and placed it inside. He covered the basket with a shawl.

“Where are you taking my child?” Devaki cried out.

Vasudeva looked at her and spoke gently, “your child?”

Then Devaki remembered what had happened just before the child was born. Lord Vishnu had appeared to them. As the couple fell at His feet, the Lord had said, “I’m going to be born as your eighth child.”

Thus, the Lord of the Universe had taken birth as her child.

Devaki joined her hands in salutation. “Govinda, you have chosen to be born to me. You show us the way.”

Vasudeva picked up the basket and placed it on his head. Everything he did was full of care and tenderness.As Vasudeva walked towards the prison door, the locks fell off, and Vasudeva walked out. Without looking at the guards who were fast asleep, he walked away, uttering the name of the Lord, “Govinda, Govinda, Govinda…”

It was the dead of night. The streets of Mathura were deserted. Not even a dog barked. Vasudeva walked unmindful of the rain. He was not even aware that a seven-headed serpent had opened its hoods over the basket like an umbrella, shielding the child from the rain.

Vasudeva headed straight to the river front. Yamuna was swelling with water. No one would dare cross the river which was rising by the minute. Saying, “Govinda, Govinda…” Vasudeva stepped into the river.

As soon as he took a step forward, the river parted, making a path for Vasudeva to cross over. Vasudeva walked, closely followed by the seven-headed serpent with its hoods spread over the basket.

As soon as Vasudeva reached the other bank of the river, he started walking towards Gokula. As he neared the house of his friend Nanda, who was the Village Chief, he found the doors open. He walked through the doors. At Nanda’s house, his wife Yashoda had just given birth to a girl child, who was none other than Devi Yogamaya. Under the spell of Yogamaya, Yashoda was fast asleep. As Vasudeva lowered the basket, baby Yogamaya smiled at the child in the basket.

Vasudeva placed his son next to the sleeping Yashoda. He picked up the girl child and placed her in the basket. He placed the basket on his head and left.

He did not even glance at the house next door where Rohini, his first wife, was living with his seventh son. He began to walk towards the river with the seven-headed serpent following him, spreading its hoods over the child in the basket. As Vasudeva approached the Yamuna, the river parted again, making a path for him to cross over.
        </item>
    </string-array>
</resources>